Finding Aid for Workshop for Armenian/Turkish Scholarship records, 1998-2011
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Workshop for Armenian/Turkish Scholarship records 1998-2011
Workshop for Armenian/Turkish Scholarship
3 linear feet
2012175 Bimu 2
Workshop organized by University of Michigan faculty that investigates the causes, circumstances, and consequences of the Armenian Genocide of 1915. Records detail the activities of the Workshop, including administrative functions and papers, materials from the Workshops themselves, and Workshop projects. Also included are materials related to the scope and topic of the Workshops.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Records were donated by the Workshop for Armenian/Turkish Scholarship (donor # 10661 ) in 2011.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open for research but certain restrictions apply to reproduction of or quotation from the records:
Unless otherwise indicated, research papers presented at WATS workshops can be reproduced or quoted from only with the expressed consent of the authors. Many of the papers presented at WATS workshops have been published as articles in journals or chapters in books.
Direct reference to or quotations from correspondence available from the WATS listserv can be used only with the expressed consent of both sender and receiver.
Direct quotations from the lectures by Professor Müge Göçek and Gerard Libaridian (course on Turkish-Armenian relations since the 19th century) as recorded in the collection can be used only with the expressed consent of the particular lecturer.
The Workshop for Armenian/Turkish Scholarship (WATS) is an ongoing effort on the part of a number of scholars, Armenian, Turkish and others, to investigate the causes, circumstances and consequences of the Armenian Genocide of 1915. The Workshop was conceived of and planned by University of Michigan professors Fatma Müge Göçek, Stephanie Platz, Kenneth Church, Kevork Bardakjian and Ronald Suny. In later years the organizing committee consisted of University of Michigan professors Müge Göçek, Suny, and Gerard Libaridian. The three transferred leadership of the Workshop to a new team of scholars in 2011.
Between 2000 and 2011, members of the Workshop met eight times in the United States and Europe to discuss, present papers, and establish a shared historical record and rough consensus on interpretation of the tragedies of the last years of the Ottoman Empire. The University of Michigan hosted the second workshop in 2002, and in 2011 the Armenian Studies Program co-sponsored the eighth workshop in Amsterdam.
The Middle East Studies Association recognized Drs. Müge Göçek and Suny and the scholars of the Workshop with the bestowing of the 2005 Academic Freedom Award, applauding their collective effort to "initiate and implement a project that overcame political divisions in society and in the academy," and noting that the Workshop "has provided a model that others addressing other conflicted histories can use in the years ahead."[1]
In 2011, a selection of the papers from the first seven workshops was published by Oxford University Press with the title A Question of Genocide: Armenians and Turks at the End of the Ottoman Empire.
-------------------
1. http://www.mesa.arizona.edu/awards/mesa-academic-freedom.html
The Workshop for Armenian/Turkish Scholarship (WATS) consists of records and related material from the WATS archives. The records are divided into five series: Administrative, Workshops, WATS Projects, and Related Materials. The collection was organized by Nora Nercessian prior to being presented to the Bentley Historical Library. The arrangement and description done by Nercessian has largely been retained.
Subjects:
Armenian massacres, 1915-1923.; Armenians--Turkey--History--20th century.; Genocide--Turkey--History--20th century.; Turkey--Ethnic relations--History--20th century.; University of Michigan. Armenian Studies Program.; Workshop for American/Turkish Scholarship.
- Administrative
  The Administrative series consists of material related to the organization of the Workshop, its history, financials, website and related correspondence. The series also contains material related to failed proposals and outside recognition of the Workshop.
  - Project Background and History (Box 1)
    - Early Discussion and Planning (Box 1)
    - Beginnings and General Overview (Box 1)
    - Interviews conducted August 2011 (Box 1)
      (includes CD)
  - WATS Papers by Author and Chronology (Box 1)
  - Participants' Biographies (Box 1)
  - WATS Reports and Related Correspondence
    - Reports (Box 1)
    - Related Correspondence (Box 1)
  - WATS Press Releases, Coverage, and Interviews
    - Press Releases and Coverage 2000-2011 (Box 1)
    - Interviews 2005-2011 (Box 1)
  - WATS Website 2005-2011 (Box 1)
  - WATS listserv 2001-2011 (Box 1)
    (includes DVD)
  - WATS Budget, Funding, Financials
    - Funding Requests and Awards 2002-2010 (Box 1)
    - Statement Balance and Statement of Activity with Detail 2005-2010 (Box 1)
    - Participants' Travel Itineraries and Expenses 2003-2006 (Box 1)
    - Partner Institution's Charges to WATS Workshops 2005-2006 (Box 1)
    - Related Correspondence (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, discussion of proposal to hold WATS at Brown University and preliminary program September 2001 (Box 1)
  - MESA Academic Freedom Award 2005 (Box 1)
  - WATS Archives and Book Presentation September 2011 (Box 1)
- Workshops
  The Workshops series consists of material related to all eight of the WATS individual workshops from 2000 to 2011. For each workshop there is general information, notes from the sessions, papers that workshop participants presented, and related correspondence. Some workshops have additional related material.
  - Workshop I: Armenians and the End of the Ottoman Empire, University of Chicago, Chicago March 17-19, 2000
    - General Information 1999-2000 (Box 1)
    - Papers, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Workshop Notes (Box 1)
    - Related Correspondence (Box 1)
  - Workshop II: Contextualizing the Armenian Experience in the Ottoman Empire: From the Balkan Wars to the New Turkish Republic University of Michigan, Ann Arbor March 8-11, 2002
    - General Information 2001-2002 (Box 1)
    - Papers, 4 folders (Box 1)
    - Workshop Notes and Summary (Box 1)
    - Public Session Notes (Box 1)
    - Related Correspondence 2001-2002 (Box 1)
  - Workshop III: Vectors of Violence: War, Revolution, and Genocide, University of Minnesota, Minneapolis March 27-30, 2003
    - General Information (Box 1)
    - Papers, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Workshop Notes (Box 1)
    - Related Correspondence 2002-2003 (Box 1)
  - Workshop IV: Ideologies of Revolution, Nation, and Empire: Political Ideas, parties, and practices at the end of the Ottoman Empire, 1872-1922. Salzburg Seminar, Institute for Historical Justice and Reconciliation April 14-17, 2005
    - General Information 2004-2005 (Box 1)
    - Abstracts 2004 (Box 1)
    - Papers, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Papers, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Fireside Chat at Salzburg (Box 2)
    - Workshop Notes (Box 2)
    - Analysis of Meeting 4 2005 (Box 2)
    - Related Correspondence 2004-2005 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence and Issues Related to Salzburg Seminar 2004-2005 (Box 2)
  - Workshop V: the Boundaries of Genocide: Intentions, Histories, Peoples, New York University, New York May 15-16, 2006
    - General Information 2005-2006 (Box 2)
    - Abstracts 2006 (Box 2)
    - Papers (Box 2)
    - Workshop Discussion Notes (Box 2)
    - Related Correspondence 2005-2006 (Box 2)
  - Workshop VI: Revisiting Ideologies and Revolutionary Practice in the Late Ottoman Empire, Graduate Institute of International Studies, Geneva, Switzerland February 27-March 1, 2008
    - General Information 2008 (Box 2)
    - Abstracts 2007-2008 (Box 2)
    - Papers, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Workshop Notes (Box 2)
    - Related Correspondence 2007-2008 (Box 2)
  - Workshop VII: From Empire to Nation: The Ottoman Case in Comparative Perspective, University of California, Berkeley March 4-6, 2010
    - General Information 2010 (Box 2)
    - Abstracts 2010 (Box 2)
    - Papers, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Workshop Notes (Box 2)
    - Public Session (Box 2)
    - Related Correspondence 2009-2010 (Box 2)
  - Workshop VIII: Ethnic Tensions and Violence at the end of the Ottoman Empire, International Institute of Social History and NIOD Institute for War, Holocaust and Genocide Studies, Amsterdam, the Netherlands October 27-30, 2011
    - General Information 2011 (Box 2)
    - Papers, 4 folders (Box 2)
- WATS Projects
  The WATS Projects series contains material related to specific projects the Workshop members undertook together in addition to the Workshops themselves. These include the editing and publishing the book A Question of Genocide: Armenians and Turks at the End of the Ottoman Empire, and a mini-project to attempt to write a common history of the town Agn/ Egin (modern-day Kemaliye) in Turkey.
  - A Question of Genocide
    - Book Proposal and Announcement 2004 (Box 2)
    - Writer's Workshop December 2007 (Box 2)
    - Publication Agreements 2008-2011 (Box 2)
    - Contributors' Biographies undated (Box 2)
    - Armenian Weekly Review 2011 (Box 2)
  - The Agn/Egin Project
    - Project Description (Box 2)
    - History of Agn/Egin (Box 2)
    - Photographs of Kemaliye (Agn/Egin) Mystical Valley, by photographer Sitki Firat (Box 2)
      (CD)
    - Additional References and Bibliographies for the History of Agn/Egin 2005-2007 (Box 2)
- Related Materials
  Related Materials include reference materials and programs from other conferences as well as publications, book reviews, and papers that share the same focus of study as WATS. Also included in this series is the syllabus and written notes from the University of Michigan winter 2007 course "Turkish/Armenian Relations since the 19th Century" taught by Gerard Libaridian and Fatma Müge Göçek as well as a proposal for the creation of a Center for Armenian-Turkish Studies at the University.
  - Papers, Studies, lectures and exchanges, 7 folders (Box 3)
  - Related Book Reviews 2003-2005 (Box 3)
  - Related Newspaper articles and interviews 1998-2006 (Box 3)
  - Related Conferences
    - "The Destruction of Armenians in the Ottoman Empire in Light of Recent Research," 2004 (Box 3)
    - "Turkey, Toward Post-Nationalism?," 2004 (Box 3)
    - In History and Beyond History. Armenians and Turks: a Thousand Years of Relations 2004 (Box 3)
    - "Ottoman Armenians During the Fall of the Ottoman Empire," 2005 (Box 3)
    - Press Coverage (Box 3)
    - Message by H.E. Abdullah Gul to Prof. Ayse Soysal 2005 (Box 3)
    - First International Symposium of Mardin History 2005 (Box 3)
    - Türkiye ve Avrupa. Türkiye Üzerine Tartismalar, (Turkey and Europe, Debates on Turkey) 2006 (Box 3)
    - International Social Studies Symposium (EUSAS) 2005-2008 (Box 3)
  - Related Organizations (Box 3)
  - Proposal for a Center for Armenian-Turkish Studies (CATS) at the University of Michigan, Ann Arbor 2002 (Box 3)
  - Global Heritage Fund, Project on the Restoration of Kars Description and Correspondence 2005 (Box 3)
  - Declaration by the Turkish Grand National Assembly April 2005 (Box 3)
  - International Center for Transitional Justice (ICTJ) Legal Analysis for the Turkish-Armenian Reconciliation Commission 2003 (Box 3)
  - Hrant Dink 2006-2007 (Box 3)
  - Course: Turkish/Armenian Relations since the 19th Century
    - Reflection (Box 3)
    - Course Syllabus (Box 3)
    - Video recordings of class lectures by Professors Fatma Müge Göçek and Gerard J. Libaridian 2007 (Box 3)
      (48 CDs)
  - Audio/Visual
    - The Armenian Genocide, prepared by the Armenian Genocide Museum Institute, National Academy of Sciences of the Republic of Armenia on the Occasion of the 90th Anniversary of the Armenian Genocide 2005 (Box 3)
    - The Armenian Genocide: 90 Years Later, directed by Stephen Feinstein, University of Minnesota, 2005 (Box 3)
      (DVD)
    - ...Turkish Soup made with Armenian Bones... date and place of production unknown (Box 3)
  - Related Books and Publications (Box 3)